<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="planning" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title>Planning an Implementation</title>
    <para>
    In the previous Chapter we presented a high level introduction to some basic concepts
    in SymmetricDS, some of the high-level features, and a tutorial demonstrating a basic, working
    example of SymmetricDS in action.
    This chapter will focus on the key considerations and decisions one must make when planning a SymmetricDS implementation. 
    As needed, basic concepts will be reviewed or introduced throughout this Chapter.  By the
    end of the chapter you should be able to proceed forward and implement your planned design.  This Chapter
    will intentionally avoid discussing the underlying database tables that capture the configuration resulting
    from your analysis and design process.    
    Implementation of your design, along with discussion of the tables backing each concept, is covered in <xref linkend="configuration" />.
    </para>
    <para>
    When needed, we will rely on an example of a typical use of SymmetricDS in retail situations.  This
                example retail deployment of SymmetricDS might include many point-of-sale workstations located at stores that may have 
                intermittent network connection to a central location.  These workstations might have point-sale-software that uses a local
                relational database.  The database is populated with items, prices and tax information from a centralized
                database.  The point-of-sale software looks up item information from the local database and also saves 
                sale information to the same database.   The persisted sales need to be propagated back to the centralized database.  
               </para>
    
    
    <section id="identifying-nodes">
    <title>Identifying Nodes</title>
    <para>
      A <emphasis>node</emphasis> is a single instance of SymmetricDS. It can be thought of as a proxy for a database 
      which manages the synchronization of data to and/or from its database. 
      For our example retail application, the following would be SymmetricDS nodes:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Each point-of-sale workstation.</listitem>
                    <listitem>The central office database server.</listitem>                   
                </itemizedlist>
      Each node of SymmetricDS can be either embedded in another application, run stand-alone, or even run in the background as a service.  
      If desired, nodes can be clustered to help disperse load if they send and/or receive large volumes
      of data to or from a large number of nodes.
      </para>
      <para>
      Individual nodes are easy to identify when planning your implementation.  If a database
      exists in your domain that needs to send or receive data, there needs to be a corresponding
      SymmetricDS instance (a node) responsible for managing the synchronization for that database.
      
      </para>

<!--  MDH : need to discuss node_id and external_id here - decide what they should be -->      
    </section>
    <section id="organizing-nodes">
            <title>Organizing Nodes</title>
            <para> Nodes in SymmetricDS are organized into an overall node network, with connections based on what data needs
            to be synchronized where.  The exact organization of your nodes will be very specific to your synchronization goals.
            As a starting point, lay out your nodes in diagram form and draw connections between nodes to represent cases in which 
            data is to flow in some manner.  Think in terms of what data is needed at which node, what data is in common to more than one node, etc.
            If it is helpful, you could also show data flow into and out of external systems.  As you will discover later,
            SymmetricDS can publish data changes from a node as well using JMS.
    </para>             
                
            <para>Our retail example, as shown in <xref linkend="figure-two-tier" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, represents a tree hierarchy with a single central office node connected
            by lines to one or more children nodes (the POS workstations). Information flows from the central office node to an individual register
            and vice versa, but never flows between registers. </para>
            <para>
                <figure id="figure-two-tier">
                    <title>Two Tiered Retail Store Deployment Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/two-tier-arch.gif" format="GIF" />
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>                
            <para>More complex organization can also be used. Consider, for example, if the same retail example is expanded to include 
              store <emphasis>servers</emphasis> in each
              store to perform tasks such as opening the store for the day, reconciling registers, assigning employees, etc. 
              One approach to this new configuration would be to create a three-tier hierarchy (see  <xref linkend="figure-three-tier-store-server" xrefstyle="select: label"/>).
              The highest tier, the centralized database, 
              connects with each store server's database. The store servers, in turn, communicate with the 
              individual point-of-sale workstations at the store. In this way data from each register could be accumulated at
              the store server, then sent on to the central office.  Similarly, data from the central office can be staged in the 
              store server and then sent on to each register, filtering the register's data based on which register it is.</para>                        
             <para>
                <figure id="figure-three-tier-store-server">
                    <title>Three Tiered, In-Store Server, Retail Store Deployment Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/three-tier-arch.gif" format="GIF" />
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>    
        <para>One final example, show in <xref linkend="figure-three-tier-regional" xrefstyle="select: label"/>, again extending our original two-tier retail use case, would be to organize stores by "region" in the world.  
        This three tier architecture would introduce new regional servers (and corresponding regional databases)
        which would consolidate information specific to stores the regional server is responsible for.  The tiers in this case are
        therefore the central office server, regional servers, and individual store registers.         
        </para>
          <para>
                <figure id="figure-three-tier-regional">
                    <title>Three Tiered, Regional Server, Retail Store Deployment Example</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/three-tier-regional-arch.gif" format="GIF" />
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>
            </para>    
        <para>
        These are just three common examples of how one might organize nodes in SymmetricDS.  While the examples above were for the retail industry, 
        the organization, they could apply to a variety of application domains.
        </para>
        </section>
        
     <section id="grouping-nodes">
       <title>Defining Node Groups</title>
       <para>
         Once the organization of your SymmetricDS nodes has been chosen, you will need to <emphasis>group</emphasis> your nodes
         based on which nodes share common functionality.  This is accomplished in SymmetricDS through the concept of a 
         <emphasis>Node Group</emphasis>.  Frequently, an individual tier in your network will represent one Node Group. 
         Much of SymmetricDS' functionality is specified by Node Group and not an individual node. For example, when it comes 
         time to decide where to route data captured by SymmetricDS, the routing is configured by <emphasis>Node Group</emphasis>. 
        </para> 
        <para>
        For the examples above, we might define Node Groups of:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>"workstation", to represent each point-of-sale workstation</listitem>
                    <listitem>"corp" or "central-office" to represent the centralized node.</listitem>
                    <listitem>"store" to represent the store server that interacts with store workstations and sends and
                        receives data from a central office server.</listitem>
                    <listitem>"region" to represent the a regional server that interacts with store workstations and sends and
                        receives data from a central office server.</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                Considerable thought should be given to how you define the Node Groups.    Groups should be created for each set of nodes
                that synchronize common tables in a similar manner.  Also, give your Node Groups
                meaningful names, as they will appear in many, many places in your implementation of SymmetricDS.
          </para>
          <para>Note that there are other mechanisms in SymmetricDS to route to individual nodes 
                or smaller subsets of nodes within a Node Group, so do not choose Node Groups based on needing only subsets of data at
                specific nodes.
                For example, although you could, you would not want to create a Node Group
                for each store even though different tax rates need to be routed to each store.  
                Each store needs to synchronize the same tables
                to the same groups, so 'store' would be a good choice for a Node Group.
          </para>
     
     </section>
     
      <section id="linking-nodes">
       <title>Linking Nodes</title>
       <para>
            Now that Node Groups have been chosen, the next step in planning is to document the individual links between
            Node Groups.  These <emphasis>Node Group Links</emphasis> establish a source Node Group, a target Node Group, and a
            <emphasis>data event action</emphasis>, namely whether the data changes are <emphasis>pushed</emphasis> or <emphasis>pulled</emphasis>.
               The push method causes the source Node Group to connect to the target, while a pull method
            causes it to wait for the target to connect to it.
        </para>
        <para>For our retail store example, there are two Node Group Links defined.  
        For the first link, the "store" Node Group pushes data to the "corp" central office Node Group.
        The second defines a "corp"
        to "store" link as a pull.  Thus, the store nodes will periodically pull data from the central office,
        but when it comes time to send data to the central office a store node will do a push.
        </para>
     </section>
     
       
     <section id="choosing-channels">
      <title>Choosing Data Channels</title>
        <para>When SymmetricDS captures data changes in the database, the changes are captured in the 
        order in which they occur.  In addition, that order is preserved when synchronizing the 
        data to other nodes.
        Frequently, however, you will have cases where you have different "types" of data with
        differing priorities.  Some data might, for example, need priority for synchronization despite
        the normal order of events.   For example, in a retail environment, users may be waiting for
        inventory documents to update while a promotional sale event updates a large number of items.
        </para>
        <para>
           SymmetricDS supports this by allowing tables being synchronized to be grouped together into <emphasis>Channels</emphasis> of data.
           A number of controls to the synchronization behavior of SymmetricDS are controlled at the Channel level.  For example,    
            Channels provide a processing order when synchronizing, a limit on the
            amount of data that will be batched together, and isolation from errors in other channels.  
            By categorizing data into channels and assigning them to <xref linkend="table_trigger" xrefstyle="table"/>s, the user gains more control and visibility into
            the flow of data.  In addition, SymmetricDS allows for synchronization to be enabled, suspended, or scheduled by Channels as well.
            The frequency of synchronization can also be controlled at the channel level.
        </para>
 <!--  MDH "Batching" should probably be discussed here, as there's a decision to be made for each channel -->
        <para>
          Choosing Channels is fairly straightforward and can be changed over time, if needed.  Think about the
          differing "types" of data present in your application, the volume of data in the various types, etc.  What 
          data is considered must-have and can't be delayed due to a high volume load of another type of data?  For example,
          you might place employee-related data, such as clocking in or out, on one channel, but sales transactions on another.
          We will define which tables belong to which channels in the next sections.          
        </para>
        
        <important>
        <para>
            Be sure that, when defining Channels, all tables related by foreign keys are included in the same channel.
        </para>
    </important>    
    </section>  
       
    <section id="defining-data-changes">
      <title>Defining Data Changes to be Captured and Routed</title>
      <para>
      At this point, you have designed the node-related aspects of your implementation, namely choosing nodes, grouping the nodes based on functionality, defining which node groups
      send and receive data to which others (and by what method).  You have defined data Channels based on the types and priority of data being synchronized.  The largest remaining
      task prior to starting your implementation is to define and document what data changes are to be captured (by defining SymmetricDS <emphasis>Triggers</emphasis>), 
      and to decide to which node(s) the data changes are to be <emphasis>routed</emphasis> to and under what conditions.  We will also, in this section, discuss the concept of
      an <emphasis>initial load</emphasis> of data into a SymmetricDS node.        
      </para>
      <section id="defining-data-changes-triggers">
       <title>Defining Triggers</title>
      
        <para> SymmetricDS uses <emphasis>database triggers</emphasis> to capture and record changes to be synchronized to other nodes. Based on the configuration you provide, SymmetricDS
        creates the needed database triggers automatically for you.  There is a great deal of flexibility in terms of defining the exact conditions under which a data change is captured.
        SymmetricDS triggers are defined in a table named <xref linkend="table_trigger" xrefstyle="table"/>.  Each trigger you define is for a particular table associated.  Each trigger can also specify:
           <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>whether to install a trigger for updates, inserts, and/or deletes</listitem>
                <listitem>conditions on which an insert, update, and/or delete fires</listitem>
                <listitem>a list of columns that should not be synchronized from this table</listitem>
                <listitem>a SQL select statement that can be used to hold data needed for routing (known as External Data)</listitem>
           </itemizedlist>
        </para>
       <para>
       As you define your triggers, consider which data changes are relevant to your application and which ones ar not.  Consider under what special conditions
       you might want to route data, as well.  For our retail example, we likely want to have triggers defined for updating, inserting, and deleting pricing information
       in the central office so that the data can be routed down to the stores.  Similarly, we need triggers on sales transaction tables such that
       sales information can be sent back to the central office.
       </para>
       </section>
       
       <section id="defining-data-changes-routers">
          <title>Defining Routers</title>
      
         <para>The triggers that have been defined in the previous section only define <emphasis>when</emphasis> data changes are to be captured
         for synchronization.  They do not define <emphasis>where</emphasis> the data changes are to be sent to.  Routers, plus a mapping between Triggers and Routers 
         (<xref linkend="table_trigger_router" xrefstyle="table"/>),
         define the process for determining which nodes receive the data changes.
         </para>
         
         <para>Before we discuss Routers and Trigger Routers, we should probably take a break and discuss the process SymmetricDS uses to keep track
         of the changes and routing.  As we stated, SymmetricDS relies on auto-created database triggers to capture and record relevant data changes into a table, 
         the
          <xref linkend="table_data" xrefstyle="table"/> table.  After the data is captured, a background process
            chooses the nodes that the data will be synchronized to.  This is called <emphasis>routing</emphasis> and it is performed by the Routing Job.
            Note that the Routing Job does not actually send any data.  It just organizes and records the decisions on where to send data in a "staging"
            table called <xref linkend="table_data_event" xrefstyle="table"/> and <xref linkend="table_outgoing_batch" xrefstyle="table"/>.
        </para>
        <para> 
            Now we are ready to discuss Routers.  The router itself is what defines the configuration of where to send a data change.  Each Router
            you define can be associated with or assigned to any number of Triggers through a join table that defines the relationship.
            Routers are defined the SymmetricDS table named <xref linkend="table_router" xrefstyle="table"/>.  For each router you define, you will need to specify:
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>the target table on the destination node to route the data</listitem>
                <listitem>the source node group and target node group for the nodes to route the data to</listitem>
                <listitem>a router <emphasis>type</emphasis> and router <emphasis>expression</emphasis></listitem>
                <listitem>whether to route updates, inserts, and/or deletes</listitem>
             </itemizedlist>
             </para>
             <para>
             For now, do not worry about the specific routing types.  They will be covered later.  For your design simply make notes of the information needed
             and decisions to determine the list of nodes to route to.  You will find later that there is incredible flexibility and functionality available in routers.
             For example, you will find you can:
             
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>send the changes to all nodes that belong to the target node group defined in the router.</listitem>
                    <listitem>compare old or new column values to a constant value or the value of a node's identity.</listitem>
                    <listitem>execute a SQL expression against the database to select nodes to
                        route to. This SQL expression can be passed values of old and new column values.</listitem>
                    <listitem>execute a Bean Shell expression in order to select nodes to route to.
                        The Bean Shell expression can use the the old and new column values.</listitem>
                    <listitem>publish data changes directly to a messaging solution instead
                        of transmitting changes to registered nodes.  (This router must be configured manually in XML as an extension point.)</listitem>
               </itemizedlist>
             
        </para>
        <para>
        For each of your Triggers, decide which Router matches the behavior needed for that Trigger.  These Trigger Router combinations will be used to
        define a mapping between your Triggers and Routers when you implement your design.
        </para>
        </section>  
             
       
        <section id="defining-data-changes-trigger-routers">
          <title>Mapping Triggers to Routers</title>
          
          <para>The mapping between Triggers and Routers, found in the table  <xref linkend="table_trigger_router" xrefstyle="table"/>, 
          defines configuration specific to a particular Trigger and Router combination.</para>

            <section id="defining-data-changes-trigger-routers-initial-load">
              <title>Planning Initial Loads</title>             
                  <para>SymmetricDS provides the ability to "load" or "seed" a node's database with specific sets of data from its parent node.  This concept is known as an <emphasis>Initial Load</emphasis> of
                  data and is used to start off most synchronization scenarios.  The Trigger Router mapping defines how initial loads can occur, so now is a good time to plan how your <emphasis>Initial Loads</emphasis> will work.
                  Using our retail example, consider a new store being opened.  Initially, you would like to pre-populate
                  a store database with all the item, pricing, and tax data for that specific store.  This is achieved through an initial load.  
                  A part of your planning, be sure to consider which tables, if any, will need to be loaded initially. SymmetricDS can also perform
                  an initial load on a table with just a subset of data.  Initial Loads are further discussed in <xref linkend="configuration-initial-load"/>.</para>
           </section>    
              
           <section id="defining-data-changes-trigger-routers-ping-back">
              <title>Circular References and "Ping Back"</title>             
                  <para>
                  When routing data, SymmetricDS by default checks each data change and will not route a data change back to a node if it originated the change to begin with.  This prevents the possibility
                  of data changes resulting in an infinite loop of changes under certain circumstances.  You may find that, for some reason,
                  you need SymmetricDS to go ahead and send the data back to the originating node - a "ping back".  As part of the planning process, consider whether you have a special case for needing ping back.  
                  Ping Back control is further discussed in <xref linkend="configuration-trigger-router-ping-back"/>.
                  </para>     
          </section>               
      </section>
      <section id="planning-registration">
          <title>Planning for Registering Nodes</title>
          <para>
          Our final step in planning an implementation of SymmetricDS involves deciding how a new node is connected to, or <emphasis>registered</emphasis> with a parent node for the first time.
          </para>
          <para>
          The following are some options on ways you might register nodes:
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>The tutorial uses the command line utility to register each individual node.</listitem>
                <listitem>A JMX interface provides the same interface that the command line utility does.  JMX can be invoked programatically or via a web console.</listitem>
                <listitem>Both the utility and the JMX method register a node by inserting into two tables.  A script can be written to directly register nodes by directly inserting into the database.</listitem>
                <listitem>SymmetricDS can be configured to auto register nodes.  This means that any node that asks for a registration will be given one.</listitem>                
               </itemizedlist>
          </para>
    </section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="defining-transformation">
      <title>Planning Data Transformations</title>
      <para>
      SymmetricDS also provides the abilty to <emphasis>transform</emphasis> synchronized data instead of simply synchronizing it.  
      Your application might, for example require
      a particular column in your source data to be mapped to two different target tables with possibly different column names.  Or, you might
      need to "merge" one or more columns of data from two indepdentent tables into one table on the target. Or, you may want to
      set default column values on a target table based on a particular event on the source database. All of these operations, and many more,
      can be accomplished using SymmetricDS' transformation capabilities.   
      </para>
      <para>
      As you plan your SymmetricDS implementation, make notes of cases where a data transformation is needed.
      Include details such as when the transformation might occur (is it only on an insert, or a delete?), which tables or columns play a part, etc.  
      Complete details of all the transformation features, including how to configure a transformation, are discussed in <xref linkend="transform-data"/>.
      </para>
      </section>

    
 
</chapter>
