<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="introduction" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <section id="intro">
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>Welcome to SymmetricDS! This User's Guide will introduce you to both basic and advanced concepts and configuration
            of SymmetricDS. By the end of this Chapter, you will have a better understanding of SymmetricDS' capabilities, and
            many of its basic concepts. This chapter also includes a hands-on, step-by-step, tutorial meant to demonstrate some of
            the potential applications for SymmetricDS.</para>
        <section id="definition">
            <title>What is SymmetricDS?</title>
            <para> SymmetricDS is an asynchronous data replication software package that supports multiple subscribers and
                bi-directional synchronization. It uses web and database technologies to replicate tables between relational
                databases in near real time. The software was designed to scale for a large number of databases, work across
                low-bandwidth connections, and withstand periods of network outage.</para>
            <para>
                The software can be installed as a standalone process, as a web application in a Java application server, or it
                can be embedded into another Java application. A single installation of SymmetricDS is called a
                <emphasis>Node</emphasis>
                . A Node is initialized by a properties file and is configured by inserting configuration data into a series of
                database tables. It then creates database triggers on the application tables to be synchronized so that database
                events are captured for delivery to other SymmetricDS nodes.
            </para>
            <para>
                SymmetricDS supports synchronization across different database platforms through the concept of database
                <emphasis>dialects</emphasis>
                . A database dialect is an abstraction layer that SymmetricDS interacts with to insulated the main synchronization
                logic from database specific implementation details.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="background">
            <title>Background</title>
            <para>The idea of SymmetricDS was born from a real-word need. Several of the original developers were, several years
                ago, implementing a commercial Point of Sale (POS) system for a large retailer. The development team came to the
                conclusion that that the software available for trickling back transactions to the general office did not meet the
                project needs. The list of problems in the requirements made finding the ideal solution difficult:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Sending and receiving data with 2000 stores during peak holiday loads.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Supporting one database platform at the store and another at general office.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Synchronizing some data in one direction, and other data in both directions.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Filtering out sensitive data and re-routing it to a protected database.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para> Preparing the store database with an initial load of data from general office.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para> The team ultimately created a custom solution that met the requirements and made the project successful. From
                this initial challenge came the knowledge and experience that SymmetricDS benefits from today.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="whats-new">
            <title>What's new in SymmetricDS 2.x</title>
            <para> SymmetricDS 2.x builds upon the existing SymmetricDS 1.x software base and incorporates a number of
                architectural changes and performance improvements. If you are brand new to SymmetricDS, you can safely skip this
                section. If you have used SymmetricDS 1.x in the past, this section summarizes the key differences you will
                encounter when moving to 2.x.</para>
            <para>The first significant architectural change involves SymmetricDS's use of triggers. In 1.x, triggers capture and
                record both data changes and the nodes to which the changes must be applied as row inserts into the data_event
                table. Thus, the number of row-inserts grows linearly with the number of client nodes. This can lead to an obvious
                performance issue as the number of nodes increases. In addition, the problem is made worse at times due to
                synchronizing nodes updating the same data_event table as part of the batching process while the row-inserts are
                being created.</para>
            <para>In SymmetricDS 2.0, triggers capture only data changes, not the node-specific details. The node-specific
                row-inserts are replaced with a new routing mechanism that does both the routing and the batching of data on one
                thread. This means we have eliminated the real-time inserts into data_event by applications using synchronized
                tables and thus database performance will improve. We have also eliminated the database contention on data_event
                since the router job is the only thread inserting data into that table. The only other access to the data_event
                table is from selects by synchronizing nodes.</para>
            <para>
                As a result of these changes, we gain the following benefits:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Synchronizing client nodes will spend less time connected to a server node,</listitem>
                    <listitem>Applications updating database tables that are being synchronized to a large number of nodes will
                        not degrade in performance as more nodes are added, and</listitem>
                    <listitem> There should be almost no database contention on the data_event table as there could be in 1.X.
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                Because routing no longer takes place in the SymmetricDS triggers, a new mechanism for routing was needed. In
                SymmetricDS 1.x, the node_select expression was used for specifying the desired data routing. It was a SQL
                expression that qualified the insert into data_event from the SymmetricDS triggers. In SymmetricDS 2 there is a
                new extension point called the data router. Data routers are configured in the router table with a router_type and
                a router_expression. We will be providing several different routers that will serve the majority of users routing
                needs, but the framework is in place for a SymmetricDS programmer to develop domain- or application-specific
                routers.
            </para>
            <para>
                Routers that are provided include:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Column Match Router - a router that compares old or new column values to a constant value or the
                        value of a node's external_id or node_id.</listitem>
                    <listitem>Sub-select Router - a router that executes a SQL expression against the database to select nodes to
                        route to. This SQL expression can be passed values of old and new column values.</listitem>
                    <listitem>Bean Shell Router - a router that executes a BSH expression in order to select nodes to route to.
                        The BSH expression can use the the old and new column values.</listitem>
                    <listitem>Xml Publishing Router - a router the publishes data changes directly to a messaging solution instead
                        of transmitting changes to registered nodes.</listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para>Since the routing and capturing of data are now performed with two separate mechanisms, the two concepts have
                been separated into separate configuration tables in the database, with a join table (trigger_router) specifying
                the relationships between routing (router) and capturing of data (trigger). This solves a long standing issue that
                some databases that only allow one trigger per table. On those database platforms, we can now route data in
                multiple directions since we only require one SymmetricDS trigger to capture data. This also helps performance in
                those scenarios, since we only capture the data once instead of once per routing instance.</para>
            <para>
                As part of the new routing job, we have introduced another new extension point to allow more flexibility in the
                way data events get batched. A batch is the unit by with captured data is sent and committed on target nodes. In
                SymmetricDS 2, batching is now configured on the channel configuration table. This provides additional flexibility
                for batching:
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>Batching can have the traditional SymmetricDS 1.x behavior of batching up to a max batch size but
                        never breaking on a database transaction boundary.</listitem>
                    <listitem>Batching can be completely tied to a database transaction. One batch per database transaction.
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>Batching can ignore database transactions altogether and always batch based on a max batch size.
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
            <para> Another significant change to note in SymmetricDS 2.x is the removal of the incoming and outgoing batch history
                tables. This change was made because it was found that over 95% of the time the statistics the end user truly
                wanted to see were those for the most recent synchronization attempt, not to mention that the outgoing batch
                history table was difficult to query. The most valuable information in the batch history tables, the batch
                statistics, have been moved over to the batch tables. The statistics in the batch tables now always represent the
                latest synchronization attempt.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>SymmetricDS Features</title>
            <para>At a high level, SymmetricDS comes with a number of features that you are likely to need or want when doing data
                synchronization. A majority of these features were created as a direct result of real-world use of SymmetricDS in
                production settings.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="notification">
            <title>Notification Schemes</title>
            <para>
                After a change to the database is recorded, the SymmetricDS nodes interested in the change are notified. Change
                notification is configured to perform a
                <emphasis>push</emphasis>
                (trickle-back) or a
                <emphasis>pull</emphasis>
                (trickle-poll) of data. When several nodes target their changes to a central node, it is efficient to push the
                changes instead of waiting for the central node to pull from each source node. When network configuration protects
                a node with a firewall, a pull configuration allows the node to receive data changes that might otherwise be
                blocked using push. The frequency of the change notification is configured by default to one minute.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="bi-sync">
            <title>Two-Way Table Synchronization</title>
            <para> In pracice, some data may require synchronization in just one direction. For example, a retail store sends its sales transactions to a
                central office, and the central office sends its stock items and pricing to the store. Other data may synchronize in both
                directions. For example, the retail store sends the central office an inventory document, and the central office
                updates the document status, which is sent back to the store. SymmetricDS supports bi-directional or two-way table synchronization
                and avoids getting into update loops by only recording data changes outside of synchronization.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="data-channels">
            <title>Data Channels</title>
            <para> SymmetricDS supports the concept of <emphasis>channels</emphasis> of data.  
                Data synchronization is defined at the table (or table subset) level, and each managed table can be assigned to a
                <emphasis>channel</emphasis> that helps control the flow of data. A channel is a category of data that can be enabled, prioritized and
                synchronized independently of other channels. For example, in a retail environment, users may be waiting for
                inventory documents to update while a promotional sale event updates a large number of items. If processed in
                order, the item updates would delay the inventory updates even though the data is unrelated. By assigning item
                table changes to the "item" channel and inventory table changes to the "inventory" channel, the changes are
                processed independently so inventory can get through.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="transactions">
            <title>Transaction Awareness</title>
            <para> Many databases provide a unique transaction identifier associated with the rows that are committed together as a transaction.
                SymmetricDS stores the transaction identifier along with the data that changed so it can play back the transaction exactly
                as it occurred originally. This means the target database maintains the same integrity as its source. Support for
                transaction identification is documented in the appendix of this guide.</para>
        </section>
        <section id="plugins">
            <title>Data Filtering and Rerouting</title>
            <para>
                Using SymmetricDS, data can be filtered as it is recorded, extracted, and loaded.
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para><!--  MDH:  Chris - this section needs updated to reflect routers and triggers and the link between -->
                            Data routing and filtering is specified using SQL expressions in the trigger configuration. The SQL
                            expressions are configured in the node_select (for real time routing) and initial_load_select (for
                            initial data loads) columns of the
                            <xref linkend="table.trigger" />
                            . The SQL expressions are used to create the SQL triggers that SymmetricDS installs to capture data
                            changes. Using this technique data can be routed to a specific node or group of nodes.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            As data changes are loaded in the target database, a class implementing
                            <literal>IDataLoaderFilter</literal>
                            can change the data in a column or route it somewhere else. One possible use might be to route credit
                            card data to a secure database and blank it out as it loads into a centralized sales database. The
                            filter can also prevent data from reaching the database altogether, effectively replacing the default
                            data loading.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Columns can be excluded from synchronization so they are never recorded when the table is changed. As
                            data changes are loaded into the target database, a class implementing
                            <literal>IColumnFilter</literal>
                            can altogether remove a column from the synchronization. For example, an employee table may be
                            synchronized to a retail store database, but the employee's password is only synchronized on the
                            initial insert.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            As data changes are extracted from the source database, a class implementing the
                            <literal>IExtractorListener</literal>
                            interface is called to filter data or route it somewhere else. By default, SymmetricDS provides a
                            handler that transforms and streams data as CSV. Optionally, an alternate implementation may be
                            provided to take some other action on the extracted data.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="transports">
            <title>HTTP Transport</title>
            <para>
                By default, SymmetricDS uses web-based HTTP in a style called Representation State Transfer (REST) that is
                lightweight and easy to manage. A series of filters are also provided to enforce authentication and to restrict
                the number of simultaneous synchronization streams. The
                <literal>ITransportManager</literal>
                interface allows other transports to be implemented. (The unit tests for SymmetricDS take advantage of this by
                using an
                <literal>InternalTransportManager</literal>
                that makes it easy to run automated tests locally.)
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="jmx">
            <title>Remote Management</title>
            <para> Administration functions are exposed through Java Management Extensions (JMX) that can be accessed from the
                Java JConsole or through an application server. Functions include opening registration, reloading data, purging
                old data, and viewing batches. A number of configuration and runtime properties are available to be viewed as
                well.</para>
            <para> SymmetricDS also provides functionality to send a SQL events through the same synchronization mechanism that is
                used to send data. The data payload can be any SQL statement. The event is processed and acknowledged just like
                any other event type.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="requirements">
        <title>Requirements</title>
        <para> SymmetricDS is written in Java 5 and requires a Java SE Runtime Environment (JRE) or Java SE Development Kit (JDK)
            version 5.0 or above.</para>
        <para> Any database with trigger technology and a JDBC driver has the potential to run SymmetricDS. The database is
            abstracted through a Database Dialect in order to support specific features of each database. The following Database
            Dialects have been included with this release:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>MySQL version 5.0.2 and above</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Oracle version 8.1.7 and above</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>PostgreSQL version 8.2.5 and above</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Sql Server 2005</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>HSQLDB 1.8</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>H2 1.1</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Apache Derby 10.3.2.1 and above</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>IBM DB2 9.5</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Firebird 2.0 and above</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            See the appendix
            <link linkend="databases">Database Notes</link>
            for compatibility notes and other details for your specific database.
        </para>
    </section>
    <xi:include href="tutorial.xml" />
</chapter>