<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Licensed to JumpMind Inc under one or more contributor license agreements. 
	See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional information 
	regarding copyright ownership. JumpMind Inc licenses this file to you under 
	the GNU General Public License, version 3.0 (GPLv3) (the "License"); you 
	may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You should have 
	received a copy of the GNU General Public License, version 3.0 (GPLv3) along 
	with this library; if not, see <http://www.gnu.org/licenses/>. Unless required 
	by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the 
	License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS 
	OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific 
	language governing permissions and limitations under the License. -->
<section version="5.0" xml:id="android" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
	<title>Synchronization to and from Android Devices </title>

	<para>
		SymmetricDS now has its web-enabled, fault-tolerant, database
		synchronization
		software available on the Android mobile computing
		platform. The Android client follows all of the same concepts and
		brings to Android
		all of the same core SymmetricDS features as the
		full-featured,
		Java-based SymmetricDS client. The Android client is a
		little bit different
		in that it is not a stand-alone application, but
		is designed to
		be referenced
		as a library to run in-process with an
		Android
		application
		requiring
		synchronization for its SQLite database.
	</para>
	<para>
		By using SymmetricDS, mobile application development is
		simplified, in that the mobile application developer can now focus
		solely on interacting with their local SQLite database. SymmetricDS
		takes care of capturing and moving data changes to and from a
		centralized database when the network is available
	</para>
	<para>
		One of the main goals of the SymmetricDS 3 release was to support
		deployment to Android devices. SymmetricDS's overall footprint was
		reduced by eliminating a number of external dependencies in order to
		better deploy to Android. Also, the database access layer was
		abstracted so that the Android specific database access layer could be
		used. This allows SymmetricDS to be efficient in accessing the SQLite
		database on the Android device.
	</para>
	<para>
		In order to convey how to use the SymmetricDS Android libraries,
		the example below will show how to integrate SymmetricDS into the NotePad
		sample application that comes with the Android ADK.
	</para>
	<para>
		The NotePad sample application is a very simple task list
		application
		that persists “notes” to a SQLite database table called
		Notes. The
		Notes table will be configured to synchronize to a
		centralized version
		of the table.  The Notes table looks as follows:
	</para>
	<para>
		<table>
			<title>Notes Table</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Column Name</entry>
						<entry>Column Type</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>_ID(PK)</entry>
						<entry>INTEGER</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>TITLE</entry>
						<entry>TEXT</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>NOTES</entry>
						<entry>TEXT</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>CREATED</entry>
						<entry>INTEGER</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>MODIFIED</entry>
						<entry>INTEGER</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</para>
	<para>
		Next, we will describe how to embed SymmetricDS in the NotePad
		application.  Eclipse 3.7.2 and Android ADK 20.0.3 were used for this
		example.
	</para>
	<para>
		To start,create the NotePad project. You do
		this by adding a new Android Sample Project. Select the NotePad
		project.
	</para>
	<para>
		<figure id="New Sample NotePad Project">
			<title>New Sample NotePad Project</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/sync-android-1.png"
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</para>
	<para>
		SymmetricDS for Android comes as a zip file of Java archives (jar
		files) that are required by the SymmetricDS client at runtime. This
		zip file ()symmetric-ds-3.4.7-android.zip) can be downloaded from 
		the SymmetricDS.org website.  The first step to using SymmetricDS in an Android
		application is to unzip the jar files into a location where the
		project will recognize them. The latest Android SDK and the Eclipse
		ADK requires that these jar files be put into a libs directory under
		the Android application project.
	</para>
	<para>
		<figure id="Sample NotePad Project">
			<title>New Sample NotePad Project</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/sync-android-2.png" width="9.5in" scalefit="1" align="center" 
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</para>
	<para>
		Unzip the symmetric-ds-x.x.x-android.zip file to the NotePad
		project directory. Refresh the NotePad project in Eclipse. You should
		end up with a libs directory that is automatically added to the Android
		Dependencies.
	</para>
	<para>
		<figure id="Jar Files Added to Libs">
			<title>Jar Files Added to Libs</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/sync-android-3.png" width="9.5in" scalefit="1" align="center"
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</para>
	<para>
		The Android version of the SymmetricDS engine is a Java class that can
		be
		instantiated directly or wired into an application via a provided
		Android service. Whether you are using the service or the engine
		directly you need to provide a few required startup parameters to the
		engine:
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><command>SQLiteOpenHelper</command> – It is best (but not required) if the
				SQLiteOpenHelper is shared with the application that will be sharing
				the SQLite database. This core Android Java class provides software
				synchronization around the access to the database and minimizes
				locking errors.
			</listitem>
			<listitem><command>registrationUrl</command> – This is the URL of where the centralized
				SymmetricDS instance is hosted.
			</listitem>
			<listitem><command>externalId</command> – This is the identifier that can be used by the
				centralized SymmetricDS server to identify whether this instance
				should get data changes that happen on the server. It could be the
				serial number of the device, an account username, or some other
				business concept like store number.
			</listitem>
			<listitem><command>nodeGroupId</command> – This is the group id for the mobile device in
				the synchronization configuration. For example, if the nodeGroupId
				is 'handheld', then the SymmetricDS configuration might have a group
				called 'handheld' and a group called 'corp' where 'handheld' is
				configured to push and pull data from 'corp.'
			</listitem>
			<listitem><command>properties</command> – Optionally tweak the settings for SymmetricDS.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</para>
	<para>
		In order to integrate SymmetricDS into the NotePad application,
		the
		Android-specific SymmetricService will be used, and we need to tell
		the Android application this by adding the service to the
		AndroidManifest.xml file. Add the following snipped to the Manifest as
		the last entry under the <![CDATA[<application>]]>
		tag.
	</para>
	<para>
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[<service android:name="org.jumpmind.symmetric.android.SymmetricService" android:enabled="true" >           
    <intent-filter>
  		<action android:name="org.jumpmind.symmetric.android.SymmetricService" />
  	</intent-filter>
</service>]]>
		</programlisting>
	</para>

	<para>
		The other change required in the Manifest is to give the application
		permission to use the Internet. Add this as the first entry in the
		AndroidManifest.xml right before the
		<![CDATA[<application> tag]]>.
	</para>

	<para>
		<programlisting>
<![CDATA[<uses-permission android:name="android.permission.INTERNET"></uses-permission> ]]>
		</programlisting>
	</para>

	<para>
		The only additional change needed is the call to start the service in the
		application. The service needs to be started manually because we need
		to give the application a chance to provide configuration information
		to the service.
	</para>

	<para>
		In NotePadProvider.java add the following code snippet in the onCreate
		method.
	</para>

	<para>
		<figure id="NotePadProvider.java">
			<title>NotePadProvider.java</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/sync-android-4.png" width="9.5in" scalefit="1" align="center"
						format="PNG" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
	</para>

	<para>
		<programlisting>
		<![CDATA[
final String HELPER_KEY = "NotePadHelperKey";

// Register the database helper, so it can be shared with the
SymmetricService
SQLiteOpenHelperRegistry.register(HELPER_KEY, mOpenHelper);

Intent intent = new Intent(getContext(), SymmetricService.class);

// Notify the service of the database helper key
intent.putExtra(SymmetricService.INTENTKEY_SQLITEOPENHELPER_REGISTRY_KEY,
HELPER_KEY);
intent.putExtra(SymmetricService.INTENTKEY_REGISTRATION_URL,
"http://10.0.2.2:31415/sync/server");
intent.putExtra(SymmetricService.INTENTKEY_EXTERNAL_ID,
"android-simulator");
intent.putExtra(SymmetricService.INTENTKEY_NODE_GROUP_ID, "client");
intent.putExtra(SymmetricService.INTENTKEY_START_IN_BACKGROUND,
true);

Properties properties = new Properties();
// initial load existing notes from the Client to the Server
properties.setProperty(ParameterConstants.AUTO_RELOAD_REVERSE_ENABLED,
"true");
intent.putExtra(SymmetricService.INTENTKEY_PROPERTIES, properties);

getContext().startService(intent);
			]]>
		</programlisting>
	</para>

	<para>
		This code snippet shows how the SQLiteOpenHelper is shared. The
		application's SQLiteOpenHelper is registered in a static registry
		provided by the SymmetricDS Android library. When the service is
		started, the key used to store the helper is passed to the service so
		that the service may pull the helper back out of the registry.
	</para>

	<para>
		The various parameters needed by SymmetricDS are being set in the Intent
		which will be used by the SymmetricService to start the engine.
	</para>

	<para>
		Most of the parameters will be familiar to SymmetricDS users. In this case
		a property is being set which will force an initial load of the
		existing Notes from the client to the server. This allows the user of
		the application to enter Notes for the first time offline or while the
		SymmetricDS engine is unregistered and still have them arrive at the
		centralized server once the SymmetricDS engine does get registered.
	</para>

	<para>
		That's all you have to do to integrate SymmetricDS with your Android
		application. Users who are adventurous or are already familiar with
		SymmetricDS can probably figure out how to setup the central
		SymmetricDS server and configuration synchronization for the Notes
		table. The second part of this article will describe exactly that. A
		few transformation goodies will be thrown in as well.
	</para>	
</section>
