<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="extensions" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title>Extending SymmetricDS</title>
     
      
        <para>
             SymmetricDS may be extended via a plug-in like architecture where extension point interfaces 
             may be implemented by a custom class and registered with the synchronization engine.  All supported extension 
             points extend the IExtensionPoint interface.  The currently available extension points are documented in the following sections.  
        </para>
        <para>
             When the synchronization engine starts up, a Spring 
             post processor searches the Spring ApplicationContext for any registered classes which implement 
             IExtensionPoint.  An IExtensionPoint designates whether it should be auto registered or not.  If the extension point 
             is to be auto registered then the post processor registers the known interface with the appropriate service.
        </para>
        <para>
             The INodeGroupExtensionPoint interface may be optionally implemented to designate that auto registered 
             extension points should only be auto registered with specific node groups.
             <programlisting><![CDATA[/**
 * Only apply this extension point to the 'root' node group.
 */
 public String[] getNodeGroupIdsToApplyTo() {
     return new String[] { "root" };
 }
]]></programlisting>             
        </para>
        <para>
             SymmetricDS will look for Spring configured extensions in the application Classpath by importing any Spring 
             XML configuration files found matching the following pattern: <literal>META-INF/services/symmetric-*-ext.xml</literal>.  When packaged in
             a jar file the <literal>META-INF</literal> directory should be at the root of the jar file.  When packaged in a war file, the <literal>META-INF</literal> directory
             should be in the <literal>WEB-INF/classes</literal> directory.
        </para>
        <section id="extensions-parameter-filter">
            <title>IParameterFilter</title>
            <para>
                Parameter values can be specified in code using a parameter filter.  Note that there can be only one parameter
                filter per engine instance.  The IParameterFilter replaces the deprecated IRuntimeConfig from prior releases.
                <programlisting><![CDATA[public class MyParameterFilter 
    implements IParameterFilter, INodeGroupExtensionPoint {

    /**
     * Only apply this filter to stores
     */
    public String[] getNodeGroupIdsToApplyTo() {
        return new String[] { "store" };
    }

    public String filterParameter(String key, String value) {
        // look up a store number from an already existing properties file.
        if (key.equals(ParameterConstants.EXTERNAL_ID)) {
            return StoreProperties.getStoreProperties().
              getProperty(StoreProperties.STORE_NUMBER);
        } 
        return value;
    }

    public boolean isAutoRegister() {
        return true;
    }

}]]></programlisting> 
            </para>
        </section>        
        <section id="extensions-data-loader-filter">
            <title>IDataLoaderFilter</title>         
            <para>
                Data can be filtered as it is loaded into the target database.  It can also be
                filtered when
                it is extracted from the source database.
            
                As data is loaded into the target database, a filter can change the
                data in a column or save it somewhere else.  It can also specify by the
                return value of the function call that the data loader should continue on 
                and load the data (by returning true) or ignore it (by returning false). One 
                possible use of the filter might be to
                route credit card data to a secure database and blank it out as it loads 
                into a less-restricted reporting database.
            </para>
            <para>
                An IDataLoaderContext is passed to each of the callback methods.  A new 
                context is created for each synchronization.  The context provides methods to 
                lookup column indexes by column name, get table meta data, and access to 
                old data if the <literal>sync_column_level</literal> flag is enabled.  The context also provides a means 
                to share data during a synchronization between different rows of data that are 
                committed in a  database transaction and are in the same channel.  It does so by 
                providing a context cache which can be populated by the extension point.
            </para>  
            <para>
                Many times the IDataLoaderFilter will be combined with the IBatchListener.  The 
                XmlPublisherFilter (in the <literal>org.jumpmind.symmetric.ext</literal> package) is a good example 
                of using the combination of the two extension points in order to create XML messages 
                to be published to JMS.
            </para>          
            <para>
                A class implementing the IDataLoaderFilter interface is injected onto the
                DataLoaderService in order to receive callbacks when data is inserted,
                updated, or deleted.
                
                <programlisting><![CDATA[public MyFilter implements IDataLoaderFilter {
                
    public boolean isAutoRegister() {
        return true;
    }
 
    public boolean filterInsert(IDataLoaderContext context,
        String[] columnValues) {
        return true;
    }
    
    public boolean filterUpdate(IDataLoaderContext context, 
        String[] columnValues, String[] keyValues) {
        return true;
    }
    
    public void filterDelete(IDataLoaderContext context, 
        String[] keyValues) {
        return true;
    }

}]]></programlisting>
            </para>
            <para>
                The filter class is specified as a Spring-managed bean.  A custom Spring XML file
                is specified as follows in a jar at <literal>META-INF/services/symmetric-myfilter-ext.xml</literal>.
                
                <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<beans xmlns="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:context="http://www.springframework.org/schema/context"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans 
           http://www.springframework.org/schema/beans/spring-beans-3.0.xsd
           http://www.springframework.org/schema/context
           http://www.springframework.org/schema/context/spring-context-3.0.xsd">
 
    <bean id="myFilter" class="com.mydomain.MyFilter"/>
     
</beans>]]></programlisting>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="extensions-table-column-filter">
            <title>ITableColumnFilter</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point to filter out specific columns from
            use by the dataloader. Only one column filter may be added per target table.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="extensions-batch-listener">
            <title>IBatchListener</title>
            <para>
            This extension point is called whenever a batch has completed loading but before
            the transaction has committed.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="extensions-acknowledge-event-listener">
            <title>IAcknowledgeEventListener</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point to receive callback events when a batch is acknowledged.  
            The callback for this listener happens at the point of extraction.
            </para>
        </section>                
        <section id="extensions-reload-listener">
            <title>IReloadListener</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point to listen in and take
            action before or after a reload is requested for a Node.  The callback for this listener
            happens at the point of extraction.
            </para>
        </section>                
        <section id="extensions-extractor-filter">
            <title>IExtractorFilter</title>
            <para>
            This extension point is called after data has been extracted, but before it has been streamed.  It
            has the ability to inspect each row of data to take some action and indicate, if necessary, that the
            row should not be streamed.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="extensions-sync-url-extension">
            <title>ISyncUrlExtension</title>
            <para>
             This extension point is used to select an appropriate URL based on
             the URI provided in the <literal>sync_url</literal> column of <literal>sym_node</literal>.
            </para>
            <para>
             To use this extension point configure the sync_url for a node with the
             protocol of ext://beanName. The beanName is the name you give the extension
             point in the extension xml file.
            </para>
        </section>        
        <section id="extensions-node-id-generator">
            <title>INodeIdGenerator</title>
            <para>
             This extension point allows SymmetricDS users to implement their own algorithms for how 
             node ids and passwords are generated or selected during the registration process.  There may be 
             only one node generator per SymmetricDS instance.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="extensions-trigger-creation-listener">
            <title>ITriggerCreationListener</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point to get status callbacks during trigger creation.
            </para>
        </section>       
        <section id="extensions-batch-algorithm">
            <title>IBatchAlgorithm</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point and set the name of the Spring bean on the batch_algorithm column of the Channel table to use.
            This extension point gives fine grained control over how a channel is batched.
            </para>
        </section>                   
        <section id="extensions-data-router">
            <title>IDataRouter</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point and set the name of the Spring bean on the router_type column
            of the Router table to use.  This extension point gives the ability to programatically decide
            which nodes data should be routed to.
            </para>
        </section>  
        <section id="extensions-heartbeat-listener">
            <title>IHeartbeatListener</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point to get callbacks during the heartbeat job.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="extensions-offline-client-listener">
            <title>IOfflineClientListener</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point to get callbacks for offline events on client nodes.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="extensions-offline-server-listener">
            <title>IOfflineServerListener</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point to get callbacks for offline events detected on a server node during monitoring of client nodes.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section id="extensions-node-password">
            <title>INodePasswordFilter</title>
            <para>
            Implement this extension point to intercept the saving and rendering of the node password.
            </para>
        </section>        
    </chapter>