<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xml:id="architecture" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <title>Architecture</title>
    <para>
        The SymmetricDS software allows for outgoing and incoming changes to be synchronized
        to/from other databases.  The node that initiates a synchronization connection is the client, and the
        node receiving a connection is the host.  Because synchronization is configurable to
        push or pull in either direction, the same node can act as either a client or a host
        in different circumstances.
    </para>
    <para>
        The SymmetricDS software consists of a series of background jobs, managers, Servlets, and services wired together
        via dependency injection using the <ulink url="http://springframework.org">Spring Framework</ulink>.
    </para>    
    <para>
        <figure>
            <title>Software Stack</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/software-stack.gif" format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </para>    
    <para>
        As a client, the node runs the router job, push job and pull job on a timer thread.  
        The router job uses services to create batches that are targeted at certain nodes.  
        The push job uses services to extract and stream data to
        another node (that is, it pushes data).  The response from a push is a list
        of batch acknowlegements to indicate that data was loaded.
        The pull job uses services to load data that is streamed from another node
        (<emphasis>i.e.</emphasis>, it pulls data).  After loading data, a second connection is made to send a list
        of batch acknowlegements.
    </para>
    <para>
        As a host, the node waits for incoming connections that pull, push, or acknowledge data changes.
        The push Servlet uses services to load data that is pushed from a client node.
        After loading data, it responds with a list of batch acknowledgements.
        The pull Servlet uses services to extract, and stream data back to the client node.
        The ack Servlet uses services to update the status of data that was loaded at a client node.  The router
        job batches and routes data.
    </para>
    <para>
        By default, data is extracted from the source database into memory until a threshold size is reached.
        If the threshold size is reached, data is streamed to a temporary file in the JVM's default temporary 
        directory.  Next, the data is streamed to the target node across the transport layer.  The receiving
        node will cache the data in memory until the threshold size is reached, writing to a temporary file if
        necessary.  At last, the data is loaded into the target database by the data loader.  This step by step
        approach allows for extract time, transport time, and load time to all be measured independently.  It 
        also allows database resources to be used most optimally.
    </para>    
    <para>
        The transport manager handles the incoming and outgoing streams of data between nodes.
        The default transport is based on a simple implementation over HTTP.  An internal transport
        is also provided.  It is possible to add other implementations, such as a socket-based transport manager.
    </para> 
    <para>
        Node communication over HTTP is represented in the following figure.
    </para> 
    <para>
        <figure>
            <title>Node Communication</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/seq-node-communication.gif" format="GIF" />
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </para>    
    <para>
        The <literal>StandaloneSymmetricEngine</literal> is wrapper API that can be used to directly start the client services only.  The 
        <literal>SymmetricWebServer</literal> is a wrapper API that can be used to directly start <emphasis>both</emphasis> the
        client and host services inside a Jetty web container.  The <literal>SymmetricLauncher</literal> provides command line tools to work 
        with and start SymmetricDS.
    </para>   
    <!-- TODO
    <section id="ch04-components">
        <title>Software Components</title>
        <para>
            <figure>
                <title>Startup Sequence Diagram</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/seq-startup.gif" format="GIF" />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
        <para>
            <figure>
                <title>Client Side Pull Sequence Diagram</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/seq-pull-client.gif" format="GIF"  />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
        <para>
            <figure>
                <title>Host Side Pull Sequence Diagram</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/seq-pull-host.gif" format="GIF"  />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
        <para>
            <figure>
                <title>Client Side Push Sequence Diagram</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/seq-push-client.gif" format="GIF"  />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>
        <para>
            <figure>
                <title>Host Side Push Sequence Diagram</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="../images/seq-push-host.gif" format="GIF"  />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
        </para>        
    </section>
     -->
    
</chapter>
